Guide to the Jack Anderson papers, 1930-2004 MS2001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jack Anderson papers
1930-2004
1969-2004
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Anderson, Jack
MS2001
248 Linear Feet 450 document boxes, 21 flat boxes, 1 record center box and 1 object
Jack Northman Anderson (1922-2005) was an investigative journalist, author, television personality, and for over 50 years the columnist behind the syndicated political column "Washington Merry-Go-Round." Cultivating sources who provided him with exclusive access to classified information, Anderson became the longest-running political columnist in America, appearing at one point in more than 1,000 American newspapers and claiming 40 million readers. He received the Pulitzer Prize for national reporting in 1972. In addition to his daily column, Anderson maintained a high-profile presence in television, radio, and magazines, and he wrote or co-wrote 17 books.
Restrictions on Access
This series contains some items that are restricted for 25 years from the date the collection was given to Gelman Library, in 2007. Restricted items have been removed from their original files, placed in parallel files, and replaced with a separation sheet. Gelman Library will open the materials beginning in 2032, which may involve having their security classifications reviewed by appropriate government agencies.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by the Anderson family in 2005.
Historical or Biographical Note
Jack Northman Anderson (1922-2005) was an investigative journalist, author, television personality, and for over 50 years the columnist behind the syndicated column "Washington Merry-Go-Round."
Anderson was born in Long Beach, CA on October 19, 1922, to Orlando and Agnes Mortensen Anderson, devout Mormons who moved the family to Utah when Jack was two years old. (Many sources, including the New York Times obituary, identify him as Jackson Northman Anderson, but this is incorrect; his given name was Jack.) He was a precocious journalist in small-town Utah. At 12 years old, he began writing the Boy Scout column for local newspaper The Deseret News, and soon graduated to covering local news for The Murray Eagle newspaper. In high school, he edited the school newspaper The Granitian while serving as president of his class.
Anderson briefly enrolled at the University of Utah until, as a practicing member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints, he undertook a mission through the American south in 1941. Upon his return, he volunteered for the Merchant Marine, first serving as a war correspondent in occupied China until 1945, when he was inducted into the Army, and then serving in the Quartermaster Corps and writing for Stars and Stripes newspaper. At war's end, a colleague in the Associated Press suggested he go to Washington, D.C. to inquire about a job with Drew Pearson, the investigative journalist who had written the daily "Washington Merry-Go-Round" column since 1932. Pearson hired Anderson in 1947.
Anderson began covering Congress for Pearson, persuading sources to tell him what happened in closed-door meetings and to give him verbatim transcripts and government documents to support his stories. He soon came to believe that government documents were being classified and hidden from the public not for national security purposes but to protect embarrassing or even illegal activity. He intended, as he described it in his autobiography Peace, War, and Politics, "to give the people an alternative to the official version of things, a rival account of reality, a measure for judging the efficacy of rulers and whether the truth is in them." Anderson ultimately became a full partner in Pearson's column, and succeeded Pearson as its author upon his death in 1969. He would write the column daily, along with a team of reporters, until 2004.
Cultivating sources who provided him with exclusive access to classified information, Anderson reported on an extraordinary range of topics and individuals in his half-century of investigative work. Topics of particular interest represented in Anderson's columns include: investigation of corruption by Senator Thomas Dodd, organized crime, the Kennedy assassination, Chappaquiddick, Watergate (Anderson published leaked grand jury testimony), U.S.-Pakistan relations during the Indo-Pakistani War (for which Anderson received the Pulitzer Prize for national reporting in 1972), fugitive Nazis, the activities of the FBI under Herbert Hoover, the white supremacist group the Liberty Lobby and other far-right organizations, the death of Howard Hughes, the ITT Corporation/Nixon Administration scandal, the ABSCAM public corruption investigation, the investigation into fugitive financier Robert Vesco, the CIA-Mafia plot to kill Fidel Castro, the Iran-Contra scandal, and the activities of innumerable Washington agencies, elected officials, and bureaucrats. For a time in 1972, Anderson was himself monitored by the CIA in the so-called "Operation Mudhen." In his columns, Anderson championed the cause of everyday Americans against the intrusions of large, sometimes corrupt institutions, motivated by the principle that (in his own words), "life is not just a struggle between evil and good but between coercion and freedom."
Day by day for over 50 years, Anderson reported on activities in Washington for the benefit of those far outside of it, breaking scandals and often raising the ire of bureaucrats in order to keep the government accountable to the people. Washington Merry-Go-Round was the longest-running political column in America, appearing at its peak in more than 1,000 American newspapers and claiming 40 million readers.
In addition to his daily column, Anderson maintained a high-profile presence in television, radio, and magazines, and he wrote or co-wrote 17 books, including his autobiography Peace, War, and Politics: An Eyewitness Account (1999). He had a daily syndicated radio show on the Mutual Broadcasting Network, reporting on many of the same topics that appeared in his columns. He was the Washington Bureau Chief of Parade Magazine, frequently contributing stories about Washington for a broad national audience. And he was a featured commentator on Good Morning America for nine years and hosted several television specials including Target: USA (1989) and Who Murdered JFK? (1988). To a generation of readers and viewers, Anderson was a household name.
Not only a journalist, Anderson was also a crusader for causes close to his heart, founding and serving on boards of nonprofit advocacy groups promoting fiscal responsibility and educational reform. Anderson co-founded the think tank and advocacy group Citizens Against Government Waste with J. Peter Grace in 1984 in order to eliminate inefficiency and mismanagement in government. He also founded the Young Astronauts Council by persuading President Ronald Reagan in 1984 to charter an organization to motivate students to focus on math and science in school. In addition, he was among the founders of the Center for the School of the Future at Utah State University.
Jack Anderson died in 2005 from complications of Parkinson's disease. He is survived by his wife, Olivia, and their nine children.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection includes articles, correspondence, index cards, book manuscripts, notes, government documents, legal documents, reports, scripts, photographs, drawings, audiovisual recordings, and artifacts that document the professional and, to a lesser extent, personal life of investigative journalist Jack Anderson. Items date from Anderson's childhood in the 1930s to 2005, the year of his death.
The materials in this collection were used and produced by Jack Anderson during every stage of his writing process, from the reporter's notes, correspondence, and research materials he gathered while working on a story, to the draft and final articles he produced, to the extensive article index he and his staff maintained. The collection also documents Anderson's work as a television and radio personality, author, frequent speaker, nonprofit leader, and even occasional cartoonist.
Cultivating sources who provided him with exclusive access to classified information, Anderson reported on an extraordinary range of topics and individuals in his half-century of investigative work. Topics of particular interest represented in Anderson's columns include: the investigation of corruption by Senator Thomas Dodd, organized crime, the Kennedy assassination, the CIA-Mafia plot to kill Fidel Castro, Chappaquiddick, Watergate (Anderson published leaked grand jury testimony), U.S.-Pakistan relations during the Indo-Pakistani War (for which Anderson received the Pulitzer Prize for national reporting in 1972), fugitive Nazis, the activities of the FBI under Herbert Hoover, the white supremacist group the Liberty Lobby and other far-right organizations, the death of Howard Hughes, the ITT Corporation/Nixon Administration scandal, the ABSCAM public corruption investigation, the investigation into fugitive financier Robert Vesco, the Iran-Contra scandal, and the activities of innumerable Washington agencies, elected officials, and bureaucrats. For a time in 1972, Anderson was himself monitored by the CIA in the so-called "Operation Mudhen." In his columns, Anderson championed the cause of everyday Americans against the intrusions of large, sometimes corrupt institutions, motivated by the principle that (in his own words), "life is not just a struggle between evil and good but between coercion and freedom."
The collection was donated by the Anderson family in 2005.
Some records in this collection are restricted for 25 years from the date the collection was given to Gelman Library, in 2007. These records include both classified government documents and materials that may reveal sources who wished to remain anonymous. Gelman Library will open the materials beginning in 2032, which may involve having their security classifications reviewed by appropriate government agencies.
Arrangement
Collection: Organized into 15 series: Merry-Go-Round columns; Index cards; Other Anderson publications; Research files; Correspondence; Television, radio, and film; Business, charity, and legal; Reporter's notes; Cartoons; Photographs; Audiovisual; Personal; Artifacts; Anderson FBI Files Obtained by National Security Archive; and Daryl Gibson research files from Peace, War, and Politics.
Related Archival Materials
The Washington Merry-Go-Round papers of Anderson's longtime collaborator Drew Pearson are held at American University Archives and Special Collections.
The personal papers of Drew Pearson are held at the Lyndon Baines Johnson Library and Museum in Austin, Texas.
The personal papers of Jack Anderson's father Orlando Anderson, which document Jack Anderson's youth and family history to some extent, are held at Brigham Young University.
Radio broadcasting -- United States; Politicians; Journalism; Politics and culture -- United States -- 20th century; United States. Congress; Anderson, Jack
- Merry-Go-Round columns, 1934-2004; 1948-2004; MS2001 Series 1; 79.5 Linear Feet 159 document boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains final typescripts as well as early typed and hand-edited drafts of syndicated Merry-Go-Round columns written by Jack Anderson and his staff. Drew Pearson originated the "Washington Merry-Go-Round" column together with Robert S. Allen in 1932. Jack Anderson joined as Pearson's associate in 1947, beginning his investigative career by uncovering secrets and crusading against corruption in Congress and the Pentagon. When Pearson died in 1969, Anderson inherited the column and soon cemented his place as Washington's premier investigative reporter by winning the Pulitzer Prize in 1972. Alongside a team of reporters, Anderson wrote Merry-Go-Round columns daily until 2004. At its peak the column appeared in over 1000 American newspapers, reaching 40 million readers a day, making Merry-Go-Round the most popular and longest running political column in the nation.
  Merry-Go-Round columns are arranged first by type of document (typescript or article draft) and then chronologically.
  Typescripts are available from 1934 through 2004. Folders are arranged chronologically by the month in which the column appeared. Arrangement within each folder is not always exactly chronological. The period from 1934 to 1947 is not well represented, nor is 1959-1960. For some time periods, the collection contains "draft typescripts" that have been marked up by hand with last-minute edits. For some time periods, it also contains "typescripts for indexing" that have been marked up for the purpose of isolating key words to add the column to Anderson's extensive column index. (Kept on index cards from 1933 to 1996, the index is now Series 2 in this collection.)
  Hand-edited drafts are available from approximately 1950 to 2004. These were not originally labeled as Merry-Go-Round columns and were not originally marked with dates but were discovered to be column drafts based on their content. It is possible that some articles for Parade Magazine or other outlets are here because they were assumed to be Merry-Go-Round columns. Folders are arranged by decade only, and even those decades were only approximations made by the processor based on their subject matter.
  Arrangement note
  This series has two subseries: Typescripts and Article drafts.
  Typescripts are arranged chronologically by the month in which the column appeared. Article drafts are arranged by chronologically by decade.
  - Typescripts, Undated
    - Typescript, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1948 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1948 August (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1948 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1948 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1948 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1948 December (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1949 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1949 February (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1949 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1949 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1949 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1949 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1949 July (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1949 August (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1949 September (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1949 October (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1949 November (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1949 December (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1950 January (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1950 February (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1950 March (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1950 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1950 May (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1950 June (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1950 July (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1950 August (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1950 September (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Typescript, 1950 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1950 November (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1950 December (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1951 January (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1951 February (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1951 March (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Typescript, 1951 April (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1951 May (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Typescript, 1951 June (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1951 July (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 July (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1951 August (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 August (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1951 September (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 September (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1951 October (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 October (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1951 November (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 November (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1951 December (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1951 December (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1952 January (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 January (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1952 February (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 February (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1952 March (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 March (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1952 April (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 April (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1952 May (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 May (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1952 June (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 June (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1952 July (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 July (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1952 August (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 August (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1952 September (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 September (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1952 October (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Typescript and Washington Post clippings, 1952 October (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1952 November (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1952 December (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1953 January (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1953 February (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1953 March (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1953 April (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1953 May (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1953 June (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1953 July (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1953 August (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1953 September (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1953 October (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1953 November (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1953 December (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1954 January (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1954 February (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1954 March (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1954 April (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1954 May (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1954 June (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1954 July (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1954 August (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1954 September (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1954 October (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1954 November (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1954 December (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1955 January (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1955 February (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1955 March (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1955 April (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1955 May (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1955 June (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1955 July (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1955 August (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Typescript, 1955 September (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1955 October (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1955 November (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Typescript, 1955 December (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 January (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 January (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 February (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 February (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 March (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 March (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 April (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 April (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 May (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 May (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 June (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 June (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 July (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 July (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 August (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 August (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 September (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 September (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 October (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 October (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 November (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 November (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1956 December (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1956 December (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 January (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 January (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 February (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 February (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 March (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 March (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 April (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 April (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 May (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 May (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 June (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 June (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/3], 1957 July (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/3], 1957 July (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [3/3], 1957 July (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 August (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 August (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 September (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 September (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 October (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 October (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 November (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 November (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1957 December (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1957 December (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 January (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 January (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 February (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 February (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 March (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 March (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 April (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 April (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 May (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 May (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 June (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 June (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 July (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 July (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 August (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 August (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 September (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 September (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 October (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 October (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 November (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 November (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Typescript [1/2], 1958 December (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Typescript [2/2], 1958 December (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Typescript, 1961 January (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Typescript for indexing, 1961 January (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Typescript, 1961 February (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Typescript for indexing, 1961 February (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Typescript, 1961 March (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Typescript for indexing, 1961 March (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Typescript, 1961 April (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Typescript for indexing, 1961 April (Box 32, Folder 4)